Guide to the Dhow Countries Music Academy collection AD.MC.139
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Dhow Countries Music Academy collection
2018-2019
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Guedes, Carlos
Dhow Countries Music Academy Zanzibar
AD.MC.139
8 audio_recordings in .WAV and .mp3 files, 183.3 GB
5 video_recordings in .mp4 and .mov files, 17.14 GB
1 Items PDF document, 23.2 MB
Consists of audiovisual recordings, chiefly of performances of taarab music by members of the Zanzibar-based Dhow Countries Music Academy (DCMA), including recordings of concerts held in Zanzibar as well as on the campus of New York University Abu Dhabi. Also included are studio recordings of individual performers, interviews, and a copy of a concert program.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by Carlos Guedes, 2024.
Arrangement
Content is arranged into three series: Documentaries, Performances, and Studio Recordings.
Historical note
The Dhow Countries Music Academy was founded in Stone Town, Zanzibar in 2002, with the aim of preserving and fostering an appreciation for traditional forms of music, such as taarab, that are unique to this region. The use of the term "dhow countries" was meant to encompass the countries and cultures along the eastern coast of Africa and the Arabian Peninsula which were traditionally bound together, commercially and culturally, through regular trade brought by the ships known as "dhows," which traveled from the Arabian Gulf and southern Arabia to ports along the Indian Ocean coast of Africa during the monsoon seasons. As such, the music--while rooted in the traditions of Zanzibar and coastal Tanzania and Kenya--has elements from such far-flung places as Kuwait, the United Arab Emirates, Yemen, Oman, and the Comoros Islands, as well as Iran, Pakistan and India.
The academy trains students in playing traditional musical instruments, such as the qanun, oud, or violin, as well as those used in other musical traditions, such as jazz, pop music, or Afro-fusion. In addition to training students at the academy, the DCMA sends members out to primary schools around Zanzibar to educate local children in these musical traditions, and gives performances at venues around Zanzibar, as well as internationally.
[Source: website of DCMA, https://www.zanzibarmusic.org/home/landing, accessed on 6 November 2024]
Content Description
The Dhow Countries Music Academy collection consists of audiovisual recordings, chiefly of performances of taarab music by members of the Zanzibar-based Dhow Countries Music Academy (DCMA), including recordings of concerts held in Zanzibar as well as on the campus of New York University Abu Dhabi. Also included are studio recordings of individual performers, interviews, and a copy of a concert program.
The recordings dated January 2018 were recorded as part of a January-term class offered by professors Carlos Guedes and Scandar Copti of New York University Abu Dhabi (NYUAD), in which they and their students traveled to Zanzibar, in order to study taarab music and the cultures with which it is linked. The recordings from this period consist of student-made video documentaries as well as audiorecordings of two separate performances at the DCMA's performance space in Zanzibar City.
The recordings created in September 2019 were related to a visit by members of the DCMA to NYUAD, in order to perform in a concert at the university's Arts Center, titled "Sufism vs. Modernism." This concert featured musicians and vocalists from the DCMA, as well as performances by Sufi vocalist Fathy Salama and Egyptian Sufi chanter Sheikh Mahmoud Tohamy. In addition to audio and video recordings of this concert, members of the DCMA were separately recorded in a studio in the Arts Center during their visit, and some of those recordings are included in this collection.
In cases where ambisonic methods of recording were used, up to 11 different microphones were placed in front of the individual performers, and individual vocal and musical tracks were created, which were then subsequently mixed into the recordings available in this collection. While the solo track performances are not included in this collection, they may be made available to researchers upon request.
Taarab; Taarab (Music) -- Zanzibar; Guedes, Carlos; Dhow Countries Music Academy Zanzibar
- Documentary films and interviews
  - The Qanun Maker of Zanzibar [1], January 2018; 1 video_recording mp4; 628 MB; 8:19 minutes (E-records AD_MC_139, Object AD_MC_139_001)
    Contents
    Short audiovisual documentary about Saidi Bhai, qanun maker from Zanzibar, done in the context of the NYU Abu Dhabi J-Term course "Audiovisual ethnography: Music and heritage in Zanzibar."
    Production
    Director: Adam Sherif Director of Photography: Ethan David Lee Editor: Ethan David Lee Sound Editors: Pranaav Parrth, Jude Al Sharif Faculty: Scandar Copti, Carlos Guedes, Andy Eisenberg Technical Instructors: Maruan Manaja, Valeriya Golovina Translations: Mahsin Basalama, Mauma Jonathan Maturege, Beatrice Mrete Nghuthu, Hurbert Shauri, Amin Elchie Virani
  - Lulu Ndani ya Chaza - The Pearl Inside the Oyster [2], January 2018; 1 video_recording mov. file, 6.02 GB; 7:30 minutes (E-records AD_MC_139, Object AD_MC_139_002)
    Short audiovisual documentary about the people from the Dhow Countries Music Academy. Voices featured in the documentary: Mitchel Strumpf, Rahma Hassan Ameyr, Samir Basalama.
    Director: Daria Zahaleanu Cinematographer and Video Editor: Sienna Hagedorn Sound MIxers and Sound Editors: Lili Janka Bognar, Gaurav Pande Production Supervisors: Valeriya Golovina, Carlos Guedes Translations: Mahsin Basalama, Mauma Jonathan Maturege, Lukoa Nemes, Beatrice Mrete Nghuthu
  - Makame Faki [3], January 2018; 1 video_recording mov. file, 1.29 GB; 8:27 minutes (E-records AD_MC_139, Object AD_MC_139_003)
    Short audiovisual documentary about Makame Fake - 'the Father of Kidumbak,' done in the context of NYU Abu Dhabi J-Term course "Audiovisual ethnography: Music and heritage in Zanzibar."
    General
    Director: Youssef Azzam Cinematographer: Febin Thapa Magar Video Editor: Adele Bea Cipste Sound Editor: Vera Ciocca Faculty: Scandar Copti, Carlos Guedes, Andy Eisenberg Technical Instructors: Maruan Manaja, Valeriya Golovina Translations: Mahsin Basalama, Salim Basalama, Lukoa Nemes, Nawal Ali
  - Professor Mitchel Strumpf, interview, conducted at Dhow Countries Music Academy [4], January 11, 2018; 1 video_recording in .mp4 format, 2.65 GB; 33:05 minutes (E-records AD_MC_139, Object AD_MC_139_004)
    Interview conducted at Dhow Countries Music Academy, in Zanzibar, as part of NYU Abu Dhabi J-term course "Audiovisual ethnography: Music and heritage in Zanzibar."
- Performances (public)
  - Stone Town, Zanzibar: concert at DCMA, part 1 (Ambisonic Mix) [11], January 8, 2018; 1 audio_recording .WAV audio file, 22.87 GB; 2:56:41 hours (E-records AD_MC_139, Object AD_MC_139_009)
    Ambisonic rendering of recordings of concerts performed in Zanzibar by the Dhow Countries Music Academy from January 2018. Mixed from recordings made by 11 separate microphones placed around the concert space.
    Mixed by Aaron Marcus Willers (July 2022).
  - Stone Town, Zanzibar: concert at DCMA, part 2 (Ambisonic Mix) [10], January 15, 2018; 1 audio_recording in .WAV audio format, 11.44 GB; 2:56:41 hours (E-records AD_MC_139, Object AD_MC_139_008)
    Mixed by Aaraon Marcus Willers (July 2022)
  - Abu Dhabi: audiorecording, Taarab and Kidumbak Concert by members of the Dhow Countries Music Academy at the Red Theater, New York University Abu Dhabi [12], September 26, 2019; 1 audio_recording in .WAV audio format, 713.4 MB; 0:43:01 minutes (E-records AD_MC_139, Object AD_MC_139_012)
    Mixed audio recording of a live performance by members of the Dhow Countries Music Academy, consisting of Zanzibari Taarab and Kidumbak music, at the NYU Abu Dhabi Red Theater.
    Performers include:
    Nima Ame = vocal; Pili Ameir = vocal; Neema Surie = violin; Mohamed Othman = violin, oud, vocal and composer; Samir Ally = Qanun and vocal; Tryphone Evarist = accordion; Fadhil Mohamed = bongos; Zainab Waziri = tablah.
    Mixed by Aaron Marcus Willers (July 2022)
    Songs performed
    1. Yalaiti = sung by Nima Ame. Originally from Siti bint Saad, recorded in the 1920's. 2. Kijiti = sung by Pili Ameir. Originally from Siti bint Saad, recorded in the 1920's. 3. Halikubaliki = composed and sung by Mohamed Othman for the first time in 2012. 4. Ashiki Baya = sung by Nima Ame. Originally from Siti bint Saad, recorded in the 1920's. 5. Alamina Dura = sung by Pili Ameir. Earliest traced recording by Bikidude in the 1980's. 6. Lulu = sung by Samir Ally. Composed and sung Professor Gogo in a recording from the 1990's (Professor Gogo is from Pemba island).
  - Abu Dhabi: videorecording, Taarab and Kidumbak Concert by members of the Dhow Countries Music Academy at the Red Theater, New York University Abu Dhabi [13], September 26, 2019; 1 video_recording in .mp4 format, 6.55 GB; 0:42:58 minutes (E-records AD_MC_139, Object AD_MC_139_013)
    Video recording of a live performance by members of the Dhow Countries Music Academy, consisting of Zanzibari Taarab and Kidumbak music, at the NYU Abu Dhabi Red Theater.
  - Abu Dhabi: printed concert program, "Sufism versus Modernism," performance by members of Dhow Countries Music Academy, with Fathi Salama and Sheikh Mahmoud Tohama, Red Theater, New York University Abu Dhabi [14], September 26, 2019; 1 Items in PDF format, 23.2 MB. (E-records AD_MC_139, Object AD_MC_139_014)
- Studio recordings (recorded at New York University Abu Dhabi)
  - Suhuba Ya Dai, written by Siti Binti Saad [27], September 27, 2019; 1 audio_recording in WAV file, 131.8 MB; 0:07:35 minutes (E-records AD_MC_139, Object AD_MC_139_027)
    Production and performers
    Ensemble: Mohamed Othman Faki: Oud and Vocals; Samir Ally Basalama: Qanun; Nima Ame: Vocals; Tryphon Evarist: Accordion; Zainab Lali: Percussion.
    Chief Engineer: Kristin Mueller; Student Engineers: Mateo Cruz, Iv치n Budnik Pereira; Mixed by Aaron Marcus Willers (June/July 2022).
  - Besera [28], September 27, 2019; 1 audio_recording in WAV file format, 120.7 MB; 0:06:57 minutes (E-records AD_MC_139, Object AD_MC_139_028)
  - Muhogo Wa Jang'ombe [29], September 27, 2019; 1 audio_recording in WAV file format, 148.2 MB; 0:08:32 minutes (E-records AD_MC_139, Object AD_MC_139_029)
  - Sikitiko [30], September 27, 2019; 1 audio_recording in WAV file format, 172.4 MB; 0:09:56 minutes (E-records AD_MC_139, Object AD_MC_139_030)
  - Interview with performers from Dhow Countries Music Academy, with Andrew Eisenberg [46], September 26, 2019; 1 audio_recording in .mp3 format, 200.4 MB; 1:23:29 hours (E-records AD_MC_139, Object AD_MC_139_046)
    Participants: Andrew Eisenberg - Interviewer; Hassan Mahenge - Saxophone and Oud; Mohammed Faki- oud; Tryphone Evarist-accordionist; Samir Salim- Qanunist; Zainab Lali- percussion; Nima Kombo- vocalist.